

Hobart, Tasmania, Australia

\$\ +61 466 683 552 | ■ toddellis.wa@gmail.com

☑ toddellis | 🛅 tmichaelellis | 🔰 tootstorm | ☑ 0000-0002-4410-8676 | 🔃 Todd-Ellis-4

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY ____

I'm a data analyst and scientist with a background in forest ecology, physical geography, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst in a wide variety of laboratory, field, and office settings across the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers; and managed complex and critical projects. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences

University of Tasmania

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2019 - present

- Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

Master of Science, Geography

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

Bellingham, WA, USA

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- · Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography / Geology

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

San Marcos, TX, USA

2007 - 2012

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

2021-02 - present

- Developing statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- · Managing design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- · Designing and implementing programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff
- Overseeing development of internal reporting and statistical packages

Adjunct Researcher Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - present

- · Developing complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- · Overseeing multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- · Managing custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- · Collaborating with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Sustainability Analyst

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2019-10 - 2021-02

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (casual)

- Processed, analysed, and reported data to promote and review institution programmes
- Developed pipelines for automating data cleaning and collation
- Prepared data and briefings for global institution rankings
- Promoted nation-wide sustainability targets using data dashboards and reports

Data & GIS Analyst Austin, TX, USA

APEX SYSTEMS: APPLE, INC. (CONTRACT)

· Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets

- · Managed and processed corporate GIS databases using data-driven software and programming languages
- Prepared statistical summaries, models, and analytical reports
- · Led research and development projects to define novel methodologies for geospatial data

2018-12 - 2019-05

Faculty Research Assistant

OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY: USDA FOREST SERVICE FORESTRY SCIENCES LABORATORY (CONTRACT)

2017-11 - 2018-06

Wenatchee, WA, USA

- Converted complex data and findings into academic and government reports
- Developed explanatory models for sustainable forest management under climate change
- Created and maintained relational databases for government research
- Gathered and analysed ecological data using statistical software

Biological Science Technician II

Ridgefield, WA, USA

WASHINGTON DEPARTMENT OF FISH AND WILDLIFE: REGION 5 (CONTRACT)

- · Applied QA/QC to develop electronic biological data collection system and relational database
- · Analysed biological fisheries data for state government research reporting
- · Collected and recorded biological data for government research and both commercial and tribal fisheries
- · Designed, built, and maintained department, fisheries, and commercial research equipment

2017-08 - 2017-11

Hobart, TAS, Australia

CONSULTING _____

2020-08 Predicting fire behaviour using historical satellite imagery
Frontier Development Lab

2019-06 Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity
USDA Forest Service

2018-08 Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate

USD\$2,500

HONOURS

Foster Parent

USDA Forest Service

2021-10 NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research AUD\$10,000 Australian Museum 2021-09 Sustainability Award University of Tasmania 2021-08 Certifi-Cat of Appreciation Ten Lives Cat Centre 2019-09 Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x) AUD\$28,000 p.a. NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub 2019-09 NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x) AUD\$5,000 p.a. NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub 2018-06 Best Fish and Wildlife Science Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife 2017-10 Conservation Award

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife

Ten Lives Cat Centre	2020-05 - present
Animal Handler	New Braunfels, TX, USA
HUMANE SOCIETY OF THE NEW BRAUNFELS AREA	2018-08 - 2019-01
Animal Handler	Wenatchee, WA, USA
Wenatchee Valley Humane Society	2018-03 - 2018-08
Technology Tutor	Wenatchee, WA, USA
North Central Regional Library	2018-01 - 2018-08
Geographic Information Systems Technician	Portland, OR, USA
PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY	2017-01 - 2017-11
Assistant Librarian	Kelso, WA, USA
BEACON HILL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL	2017-01 - 2017-11